The Lives of the Prophets; Part 1
اَلْحَمْدُ لله ، وَالصَّلَاةُ وَالسَّلَامُ عَلى سَيِّدِنَا محمد وَعَلَى اَلِهِ وَصَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ
Syedina Yaqub عليه السّلام requested his sons; to go look for Yusuf(يوسُف) and his brother Binyamin(بنيامين);
Because he never lost hope in Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
And the next year they went to Egypt to receive the ration.
And they carried with them their merchandise that was sent back with them from the year before.
They went to SadyinaYusuf عليه السّلام and they met with him and they said;
فَلَمَّا دَخَلُوا عَلَيْهِ قَالُوا يَا أَيُّهَا الْعَزِيزُ مَسَّنَا وَأَهْلَنَا الضُّرُّ وَجِئْنَا بِبِضَاعَةٍ مُزْجَاةٍ فَأَوْفِ لَنَا الْكَيْلَ وَتَصَدَّقْ عَلَيْنَا
إِنَّ اللَّهَ يَجْزِي الْمُتَصَدِّقِينَ۝
Then when they entered unto him, they said;
Oh ruler of the land; A hard time has hit us and our family, difficult moments.
It was famine and it was continuing from year to year, and it's becoming more difficult throughout time;
and things were becoming more constrained and more severe.
So they went to SadyinaYusuf(سَيِّدنا يوسُف) and they were begging him.
مَسَّنَا وَأَهْلَنَا الضُّرُّ
Harm has befalled us with our families.
وَجِئْنَا بِبِضَاعَةٍ مُزْجَاةٍ
And we have came with poor capital.
Bidhaa Muzjaa(بِبِضَاعَةٍ مُزْجَاةٍ) means some merchandise that is not very good quality.
Something that is not worth a lot.
So they're telling Al-Aziz(ألعزيز);
Al-Aziz(ألعزيز) which is SadyinaYusuf(سَيِّدنا يوسُف) and that's the name of this position.
Al-Aziz(ألعزيز) and the word Al-Aziz(ألعزيز) itself means; the honored.
And they're telling him; really we want you to help us
because this merchandise that we brought with us is not worth a lot; It's not even worth presenting to you;
so they're apologizing before they even present it because they know that it's worthless.
وَجِئْنَا بِبِضَاعَةٍ مُزْجَاةٍ فَأَوْفِ لَنَا الْكَيْلَ
So pay us full measure.
And then they said;
وَتَصَدَّقْ عَلَيْنَا
And be charitable to us.
They're asking for Sadaqah(صدقة).
They're asking for charity.
When SadyinaYusuf عليه السّلام saw his brothers begging;
When he saw that they reached to the level of begging;
Subhan Allah(سُبْحان الله) look at this; These brothers who made the conspiracy to get rid of him and kill him.
So they reached to the level of weakness where they are begging their brother whom they don't know.
And they're telling him; Give us charity.
And they said;
إِنَّ اللَّهَ يَجْزِي الْمُتَصَدِّقِينَ۝
Truly Allah does reward charitable.
At that point, when Yusuf(يوسُف) saw his brothers begging, he didn't want it to go any further.
He didn't want them to go under that level.
I mean, that's it when you beg, that's the lowest it could get and the weakest.
And he did not want to see his brothers in that position.
Even though they harmed him and they caused them all of this trouble and they throw him in the well.
And they tried to kill him and he's their brother.
But I didn't want to see them in that position of beggars.
So he said;
قَالَ هَلْ عَلِمْتُم مَّا فَعَلْتُم بِيُوسُفَ وَأَخِيهِ إِذْ أَنتُمْ جَاهِلُونَ۝
He said; Do you know; What you have done to Yusuf(يوسُف) and his brother.
إِذْ أَنتُمْ جَاهِلُونَ۝
When you were ignorant.
Do you know what you have done to Yusuf(يوسُف) and his brother.?
Who can say this except Yusuf(يوسُف) himself?
Who knows about Yusuf(يوسُف).
How Al-Aziz(ألعزيز) know about that?
So immediately when he said that they realize that they're speaking to Yusuf(يوسُف).
When he asked them, What have you done with Yusuf(يوسُف) and his brother?
They knew that the man who's standing in front of them is Yusuf عليه السّلام.
They said;
قَالُوا أَإِنَّكَ لَأَنْتَ يُوسُفُ ۖ قَالَ أَنَا يُوسُفُ وَهَٰذَا أَخِي ۖ قَدْ مَنَّ اللَّهُ عَلَيْنَا ۖ
They said; Are you indeed Yusuf(يوسُف),
قَالَ أَنَا يُوسُفُ وَهَٰذَا أَخِي
I am Yusuf(يوسُف) and this is my brother.
قَدْ مَنَّ اللَّهُ عَلَيْنَا
Allah has indeed been gracious to us.
I want you to pay attention to the following segments of the Ayah(آية).
If you would forget everything that we said in the story of Yusuf(يوسُف); make sure that you don't forget this.
Because this is the essence of the story of Yusuf(يوسُف).
This is the essence of the story of Yusuf(يوسُف).
And keep in mind that this story was revealed to Rasool Allah ﷺ when?
When was Surah(سورة) Yusuf(يوسُف) revealed?
In Makkah;
When in Makkah?
In the Aam Il Huzn(عام الهزن);
In the Aam Il Huzn(عام الهزن); When Abu Talib(ابو طالب) passed away;
and Khadijah رضي الله عنها  passed away;
and Rasool Allah ﷺ found no one to support him with strength like his Uncle Abu Talib(ابوطالب);
and no one to support him financially like his wife Khadijah(خديجه),
that was the year of sorrow.
It's not only sorrow and sadness on Rasool Allah ﷺ because he lost his uncle and he lost his beloved wife.
But because the Da'wah(دعوة) was limited and now barriers were being erected in the face of Rasool Allah ﷺ;
before that Rasool Allah ﷺ had strength;
His uncle was providing him with an umbrella and his wife was comforting him at home.
Now Rasool Allah ﷺ has lost these two supporters
and the heart of Rasool Allah ﷺ was filled with sadness and sorrow.
Those moments that Rasool Allah ﷺ was going through are unbearable.
So Rasool Allah ﷺ is receiving Surat Yusuf(سورة يوسُف);
In this particular situation because that is what Qur'an;
لِنُثَبِّتَ بِهِ فُؤَادَكَ
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى when he said will reveal in Quran; Why?
So that We would strengthen your heart.
So Quran was being revealed on Rasool Allah ﷺ in the appropriate times;
for the appropriate situations to serve the appropriate purpose.
So in that specific period of Aam Il Huzn(عام الهزن);
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى reveals to Rasool Allah ﷺ the story of Yusuf(يوسُف);
it is the story of someone; who went through difficulty, trials, Misery, sorrow and sadness.
But then in the end;
قَدْ مَنَّ اللَّهُ عَلَيْنَا
Allah has bestowed His blessing on me.
Why?
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says in this segment of the Ayah(آية);
The essence of the Surah(سورة) of Yusuf(يوسُف);
إِنَّهُ مَنْ يَتَّقِ وَيَصْبِرْ فَإِنَّ اللَّهَ لَا يُضِيعُ أَجْرَ الْمُحْسِنِينَ۝
Verily, He who has Taqwa(تقوى) and is patient, Allahسُبحانه وتعالى will not waste the deeds of  Al-Muhsineen(محسنين), the right doers.
If you have Taqwa(تقوى) and patience; Eventually you will win; even after a while.
If you have Taqwa(تقوى) and patience, no matter what, in the end, you will be victorious
and you should have no doubt in that.
SadyinaYusuf(سَيِّدنا يوسُف) was victorious in the end; In Duniyah(دُنِيَّا) and in Akhirah(آخرة).
It's not only in Duniyah(دُنِيَّا); It's In Duniyah(دُنِيَّا) and in Akhirah(آخرة).
But it happened after a while it took a while.
It wasn't swiftly in the same day; It took a while.
Therefore, it needs patience.
If you do not have patience, you will not be able to survive the long road.
So Allahسُبحانه وتعالى is telling Rasool Allah ﷺ;
There's a lot of struggling; There's a lot of striving;
But if you have patience and you have Taqwa(تقوى), Allahسُبحانه وتعالى will establish you on the land.
And Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says about Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل);
وَجَعَلْنَا مِنْهُمْ أَئِمَّةً يَهْدُونَ بِأَمْرِنَا لَمَّا صَبَرُواْ ۖ وَكَانُواْ بِـَٔايَٰتِنَا يُوقِنُونَ۝
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى said; We have made the children of Israel(اسرائيل), Aimma(أئمَّة); leaders,
leaders whom you follow in righteousness.
أَئِمَّةً يَهْدُونَ بِأَمْرِنَا
They guide to our path;
When?
When were the children of Israel(اسرائيل) leaders for mankind?
لَمَّا صَبَرُواْ ۖ
When they had patience;
وَكَانُواْ بِـَٔايَٰتِنَا يُوقِنُونَ۝
And they had Yaqeen(يقين).
There is no victory without Sabr(صبر).
إنَّ نَصَر مع الصبر
It is mentioned in a Hadith(حديث); Victory comes with patience.
And in general, today; We are very emotional.
We are fired up fast.
There could be a very hot Khutba(خطبه) of Jumu'ah(جُمعه) talking about Jihad(جهاد) for example.
During that Khutba(خطبة) everyone feels that he is like Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد).
He's ready to go in the battlefield.
The Salah(صلاة) is over; a few moments just by the time you step your foot out of the Masjid(مسجد);
You leave all of that emotions behind you, and you're back to Duniyah(دُنِيَّا) again.
Very easily fired up; and very easily we cool down.
That is not Sabr(صبر); that is not Sabr(صبر).
We are reactionary.
We act to situations; But then after a while, we'll calm down, and it's back to usual.
But with Sahabah رضي الله عنهم; they had a plan.
And they implemented that plan steadily.
And they worked on it, and eventually they were victorious.
Not only does this work with the believers, this is a law of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى; that can even be applied to the Non-believer.
Antara Bin Shaddad(أنترة بن شداد) is a famous figure in the Arab tales.
As somebody who was very courageous, that's the personality of Antara(أنترة) in the Arabic literature.
They say that Antara Bin Shaddad(أنترة بن شداد); A very strong well built powerful man came to him and said;
Antara(أنترة), how come, you are famous as being powerful and strong when your body is smaller than mine;
And your strength is less than my strength;
Nevertheless, everyone uses you as the example of courage and strength.
He said; I'll tell you why.?
Stick your finger in my mouth and I'll stick my finger in your mouth and let's bite.
I'll bite your finger and you bite mine.
Both of them; they stick their fingers in each other's mouth, and they counted to three and they started biting
and they're crushing on the fingers of each other.
After a few moments; the other guy screamed, and he lost.
Antara(أنترة) told him: That's why.?
If you would have just waited for one more moment, one more second, I would have screamed.
It's just a matter of outdoing you;
I was able to have patience for just one more moment and that's why I won.
As I say in English; Who blinks first,
إِنَّهُ مَنْ يَتَّقِ وَيَصْبِرْ فَإِنَّ اللَّهَ لَا يُضِيعُ أَجْرَ الْمُحْسِنِينَ۝
قَالُواْ تَٱللَّهِ لَقَدۡ ءَاثَرَكَ ٱللَّهُ عَلَيۡنَا وَإِن كُنَّا لَخَٰطِـِٔينَ۝
Now they realize their loss and they said;
By Allah; Indeed Allah has preferred you above us and we certainly have been sinners.
These brothers who were jealous of Yusuf(يوسُف), so jealous they tried to kill him.
Now they're saying you're better than us.
You are better than us; In the end they had to admit it.
See how Allah made him victorious in every aspect.
They even reach to the level where his brothers said; You are better than us; Now we admit.
قَالَ لَا تَثۡرِيبَ عَلَيۡكُمُ ٱلۡيَوۡمَۖ يَغۡفِرُ ٱللَّهُ لَكُمۡۖ وَهُوَ أَرۡحَمُ ٱلرَّـٰحِمِينَ۝
When Rasool Allah ﷺ went into Makkah.
He went into Makkah victorious without any parades;
without any national anthem;
without any red carpet;
without any motorcade;
without any pride;
Rasool Allah ﷺ instead of riding on his horse or camel with his chest forward, carrying his spear.
Rasool Allah ﷺ went into Makkah, making Sujood(سجود) to Allahسُبحانه وتعالى on his camel;
Until his beard was touching the back of the camel;
Tawadhua(تواضع) humbleness with Sakeena(سكينة) calmness.
Until he reached to Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه), and he climbed on the door of Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه);
while the people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) are surrounding him.
His enemy for years and years are now under the sword of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
So Rasool Allah ﷺ asked them; What Do you think I will do with you?
They said;
أَخٌ كَرِيمٌ، وَابْنُ أَخٍ كَرِيمٍ،
A noble brother and the son of a noble brother.
Today I will tell you, like what Yusuf(يوسُف) told his brother;
لَا تَثۡرِيبَ عَلَيۡكُمُ ٱلۡيَوۡمَۖ
I'm gonna tell you just what Yusuf(يوسُف) told his brother;
Today; there's no punishment or no blame on you.
اذهبوا فأنتم الطلقاء
Go; You are free.
He said; No reproach on you this day; May Allah forgive you;
And He is the Most Merciful of those who showed mercy.
So he forgave his brothers, and he allowed them to leave.
But he gave them something.
And this is a miracle of the Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء).
He gave them his shirt.
And he said; Throw it on my father, and he will see;
Because his father was blind.
Why was he blind, crying on SadyinaYusuf(سَيِّدنا يوسُف).
And this is a miracle of SadyinaYusuf(سَيِّدنا يوسُف).
ٱذۡهَبُواْ بِقَمِيصِي هَٰذَا فَأَلۡقُوهُ عَلَىٰ وَجۡهِ أَبِي يَأۡتِ بَصِيرٗا وَأۡتُونِي بِأَهۡلِكُمۡ أَجۡمَعِينَ۝
Go with this shirt of mine and cast it over the face of my father;
He will become clear sighted and bring to me all your family.
When the caravan was leaving out of Egypt;
Yaqoob(يعقوب) was in Ash-Sham(ألشَّام) very far away a few hundred miles away;
When the caravan just started moving out of Egypt;
Syedina(سيدنا) Yaqoob(يعقوب) smelled SadyinaYusuf(سَيِّدنا يوسُف).
He was smelling his shirt.
And it was still in Egypt and this is another miracle of Syedina Yaqoob عليه السّلام.
وَلَمَّا فَصَلَتِ ٱلۡعِيرُ قَالَ أَبُوهُمۡ إِنِّي لَأَجِدُ رِيحَ يُوسُفَۖ لَوۡلَآ أَن تُفَنِّدُونِ۝
And when the caravan departed, their father said; I do indeed feel the smell of Yusuf(يوسُف);
If only you think me not a dotard;
A person who has weakness of mind because of old age.
They said;
قَالُواْ تَٱللَّهِ إِنَّكَ لَفِي ضَلَٰلِكَ ٱلۡقَدِيمِ۝
This is something that one of the Mufassireen(مفسرين) of Qur'an said;
لقد قال الذي كلمة العظيمة
They have said something inappropriate to their father.
They said oh our father;
By Allah certainly you are in your old error.
They told him; You had became old; You're starting to lose your mind.
فَلَمَّآ أَن جَآءَ ٱلۡبَشِيرُ أَلۡقَىٰهُ عَلَىٰ وَجۡهِهِۦ فَٱرۡتَدَّ بَصِيرٗاۖ
قَالَ أَلَمۡ أَقُل لَّكُمۡ إِنِّيٓ أَعۡلَمُ مِنَ ٱللَّهِ مَا لَا تَعۡلَمُونَ۝
Then when the bearer of the glad tidings arrived, he cast it over his face and he became clear sighted;
He said; Did I not say to you I know from Allah that which you know not.
And now they realize their mistake again they said;
قَالُواْ يَـٰٓأَبَانَا ٱسۡتَغۡفِرۡ لَنَا ذُنُوبَنَآ إِنَّا كُنَّا خَٰطِـِٔينَ۝
O; our father asked for forgiveness from Allah for our sins; Indeed we have been sinners.
قَالَ سَوۡفَ أَسۡتَغۡفِرُ لَكُمۡ رَبِّيٓۖ إِنَّهُۥ هُوَ ٱلۡغَفُورُ ٱلرَّحِيمُ۝
He said; I will ask my Lord for forgiveness for you.
Verily He only is the One, Who's oft-Forgiving, the Most Merciful.
Now all of them moved, they took their belongings, everything with them and they started moving towards Egypt.
To fulfill the invitation of SadyinaYusuf عليه السّلام.
As soon as they came in, SadyinaYusuf(سَيِّدنا يوسُف) has prepared to meet his family.
فَلَمَّا دَخَلُواْ عَلَىٰ يُوسُفَ ءَاوَىٰٓ إِلَيۡهِ أَبَوَيۡهِ وَقَالَ ٱدۡخُلُواْ مِصۡرَ إِن شَآءَ ٱللَّهُ ءَامِنِينَ۝
Then when they entered onto Yusuf(يوسُف), he took his parents to himself and said;
Enter Egypt if Allah will; in security.
And he had the throne; SadyinaYusuf(سَيِّدنا يوسُف) was sitting on a high throne.
So he elevated his father and his mother to sit with him on the throne.
And then all of them the father and the mother, and the 11 brothers made Sujood(سجود) to SadyinaYusuf عليه السّلام;
To fulfill the dream, which he saw when he was a child.
So the end of the Surah(سورة) of Yusuf(يوسُف) fulfills the dream, which was in the beginning of the Surah(سورة) of Yusuf(يوسُف)
between them; very long lifespan, the scholars have given it 30 years, some of them 25, some of them 80 years;
Allah Ho Alam(الله اعلم).
This is the fulfillment of the dream of SadyinaYusuf(سَيِّدنا يوسُف).
إِذۡ قَالَ يُوسُفُ لِأَبِيهِ يَـٰٓأَبَتِ إِنِّي رَأَيۡتُ أَحَدَ عَشَرَ كَوۡكَبٗا وَٱلشَّمۡسَ وَٱلۡقَمَرَ رَأَيۡتُهُمۡ لِي سَٰجِدِينَ۝
I see 11 planets making Sujood(سجود) to me and the sun and the moon.
So these 11 planets were his brothers, and the sun is his father and the moon is his mother.
وَقَالَ يَـٰٓأَبَتِ هَٰذَا تَأۡوِيلُ رُءۡيَٰيَ مِن قَبۡلُ قَدۡ جَعَلَهَا رَبِّي حَقّٗاۖ
O my father; This is the interpretation of my dream of old, my Lord has made it come true.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
وَقَدۡ أَحۡسَنَ بِيٓ إِذۡ أَخۡرَجَنِي مِنَ ٱلسِّجۡنِ وَجَآءَ بِكُم مِّنَ ٱلۡبَدۡوِ مِنۢ بَعۡدِ أَن نَّزَغَ ٱلشَّيۡطَٰنُ بَيۡنِي وَبَيۡنَ إِخۡوَتِيٓۚ
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says; These are the words of Yusuf(يوسُف);
He was indeed good to me;
When He took me out of the prison,
and brought me here out of the bedouin life;
After Satan has sown enmity between me and my brothers;
Certainly in my Lord is the Most courteous and kind unto whom He will.
Truly He only He is the All Knowing, the All Wise.
رَبِّ قَدۡ ءَاتَيۡتَنِي مِنَ ٱلۡمُلۡكِ وَعَلَّمۡتَنِي مِن تَأۡوِيلِ ٱلۡأَحَادِيثِۚ
فَاطِرَ ٱلسَّمَٰوَٰتِ وَٱلۡأَرۡضِ أَنتَ وَلِيِّۦ فِي ٱلدُّنۡيَا وَٱلۡأٓخِرَةِۖ تَوَفَّنِي مُسۡلِمٗا وَأَلۡحِقۡنِي بِٱلصَّـٰلِحِينَ۝
My Lord, you have indeed bestowed on me the sovereignty, and taught me the interpretation of dreams,
the only Creator of the heavens and the earth;
You are my Wali(ولي) in this world and the hereafter.
SadyinaYusuf(سَيِّدنا يوسُف) had everything a seeker of this world wants.
I mean; No matter how hard we work, you can't get anything better than what Yusuf(يوسُف) had;
In terms of the standards of this world.
He had power and authority.
He was combined with his parents and family again, and the dispute among them was solved.
He had wealth.
He had control over the kingdom of Egypt, which was the greatest kingdom of the time.
He had it all.
If somebody had; what Yousuf عليه السّلام had; He would hold it, with his teeth and nails.
And not want to leave it.
You remember; When Suleman Ibn Malik(سليمان إبن عبدالملك) asked Abu Hazim(أبوحازم); Why do we hate death?
What did Abu Hazim(أبوحازم) say? He said;
عمرتم دنياكم وخربتم آخرتكم فتكرهون ان تخرجومن العمران الى الخراب
He said; You have built this world and you have destroyed Aakhirah(آخِرة).
So you hate to go from what is built, to what is destroyed.
SadyinaYusuf عليه السّلام had everything that a person would want in Duniyah(دُنِيَّا).
But this for SadyinaYusuf(سَيِّدنا يوسُف) is nothing.
He's not a seeker of Duniyah(دُنِيَّا).
He would say; Alhamdulillah(ألحمدلله) for what Allahسُبحانه وتعالى has given me;
but he's doing it as a Ibadah(عبادة) for Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
So Yusuf(يوسُف) when he is in the pinnacle and the peak of his power and fame and wealth and dominance on the face of the earth;
Look at the Dua(دُعَا) of SadyinaYusuf(سَيِّدنا يوسُف).
Look at the Dua(دُعَا), that SadyinaYusuf(سَيِّدنا يوسُف) is saying; He said;
تَوَفَّنِي مُسۡلِمٗا وَأَلۡحِقۡنِي بِٱلصَّـٰلِحِينَ۝
SadyinaYusuf عليه السّلام said; Cause me to die as a Muslim and join me with the righteous.
You have Kingdom; you have power; you have fame; you have wealth; you have love in the hearts of everyone;
Duniyah(دُنِيَّا) in his eyes is nothing.
Subhan Allah Hil Azeem(سُبْحان الله العظيم)
and we have a few dollars and we're clinging to it;
And we're afraid of death; for Mataa Qalil(متاع قليل);
Mataa An-Zail(متاع زائل) for something that is going to leave.
And we're holding tight to it.
SadyinaYusuf(سَيِّدنا يوسُف) has all of this and he is saying;
تَوَفَّنِي مُسۡلِمٗا وَأَلۡحِقۡنِي بِٱلصَّـٰلِحِينَ۝
Make me die as a Muslim and be with the righteous.
These are the hearts who were attached to Allahسُبحانه وتعالى and attached to Aakhirah(آخِرة).
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
ذَٰلِكَ مِنۡ أَنۢبَآءِ ٱلۡغَيۡبِ نُوحِيهِ إِلَيۡكَۖ وَمَا كُنتَ لَدَيۡهِمۡ إِذۡ أَجۡمَعُوٓاْ أَمۡرَهُمۡ وَهُمۡ يَمۡكُرُونَ۝
This is of the news of the unseen, which we reveal by inspiration to you;
you were not present with them; when they raised their plan together and also while they were plotting.
وَمَآ أَكۡثَرُ ٱلنَّاسِ وَلَوۡ حَرَصۡتَ بِمُؤۡمِنِينَ۝
And most of mankind will not believe even if you desire, eagerly.
We'll start now with a story of a Nabi(نَبِي) of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى;
who was not mentioned in reference to Da'wah(دعوة).
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى when He talked about Noah(نوح), it was the Da'wah(دعوة) of Noah(نوح).
When He talked about Hood(هود); it was the Da'wah(دعوة) of Hood(هود).
Salih(صالح); it was the Da'wah(دعوة) of Salih(صالح).
Noah(نوح); it was the Da'wah(دعوة) of Noah(نوح).
But with this particular Nabi(نَبِي); Allahسُبحانه وتعالى did not talk about his Da'wah(دعوة) at all.
Syedina Ayub عليه السّلام.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى; when he talked about Syedina Ayub(سيدنا ايوب);
He did not mention his Da'wah(دعوة) to his people.
But Allahسُبحانه وتعالى mentioned the story of his Sabr(صبر), his patience.
And that alone deserved his story to be mentioned twice and Qur'an;
In reference of his patience, so it became later proverb; Sabr Ayub(صبرايوب).
Whenever we want to describe patience, we say patience of Ayub(أيوب);
He became the symbol of Sabr(صبر); patience.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
وَٱذْكُرْ عَبْدَنَآ أَيُّوبَ إِذْ نَادَىٰ رَبَّهُۥٓ أَنِّى مَسَّنِىَ ٱلشَّيْطَٰنُ بِنُصْبٍۢ وَعَذَابٍ۝
And remember Our slave; Job; when he invoked his Lord saying;
Verily, Satan has touched me with distress and torment.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says in Surat Al-Ambiyaa(سورة الأنبِيَاء).
وَأَيُّوبَ إِذْ نَادَىٰ رَبَّهُ أَنِّي مَسَّنِيَ الضُّرُّ وَأَنتَ أَرْحَمُ الرَّاحِمِينَ۝
And remember Ayub(أيوب); when he cried to his Lord;
Verily distress has seized me and you are the Most Merciful of those who show mercy.
Ibn Abbas(إبن عباس) says that Syedina Ayub عليه السلام was very wealthy
and he had a large family and he was very healthy and strong.
So he had health, wealth and family.
And then suddenly; Syedina Ayub عليه السّلام lost his family somehow; lost his wealth and he lost his health.
And this did not happen; gradually; It happened suddenly. He lost everything.
He lost everything that a person loves in Duniyah(دُنِيَّا).
المال والبنون زينة الحياة الدنيا
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says; Children and wealth are the adornment of this life.
Whether you are Muslim or non Muslim, this is something that Allahسُبحانه وتعالى has put the love in your heart;
Your wealth and your family.
It's something that we love in this world, and that is the Zeenah(زينة); that is the adornment of this world.
Ayub(أيوب) lost these two and in addition to that, he lost his health
and his health situation became so bad;
that he was not able to move, he was not able to work
and then the particular type of disease that he had was a disease that the people used to view in a form of Tashaum(تشاعم);
they used to have a bad omen or evil Omen from this and they used to despise that particular disease.
And anybody who's inflicted with it, they will stay away from him.
So he became an outcast in the society.
And it is said that they even forced him out of the village;
So he was living outside of his town.
He had no source of income.
So it is said that his wife started to work.
She would cook for people serve them in their homes,
but then the people did not want to interact with her because they were afraid that she could also infect them.
So nobody wants to hire her.
So the situation of Syedina Ayub(سيِّدنا أيوب) was deteriorating.
And this was over a span of years; It was not a matter of a few weeks or months.
And it said that even the close ones around him his wife and his brothers and his family were saying;
If Allahسُبحانه وتعالى has any love for him, this wouldn't have happened to him.
That was difficult for Syedina Ayub(سيِّدنا أيوب) to hear
and that is when Syedina Ayub(سيِّدنا أيوب) made his Dua(دُعَا) to Allahسُبحانه وتعالى and said;
Harm has inflicted me and you are the Most Merciful.
And then Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
فَاسْتَجَبْنَا لَهُ
We responded to his Dua(دُعَا).
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى accepted the Dua(دُعَا) of Syedina Ayub عليه السّلام.
How did it happen?
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى told him;
ارْكُضْ بِرِجْلِكَ ۖ هَٰذَا مُغْتَسَلٌ بَارِدٌ وَشَرَابٌ۝
Strike the ground with your foot; This is a spring of water to wash in cool and refreshing to drink.
So he was commanded to hit the ground with his foot.
So water came out;
He was ordered by Allahسُبحانه وتعالى to wash his body with that water;
So it would heal him and purify him from the outside and to drink it and it will heal him from the inside.
So that replace the health of Syedina Ayub(سيِّدنا أيوب).
And the Ayah(آية) says;
وَوَهَبْنَا لَهُ أَهْلَهُ وَمِثْلَهُم مَّعَهُمْ رَحْمَةً مِّنَّا وَذِكْرَىٰ لِأُولِي الْأَلْبَابِ۝
And We have given him a replacement of his family like them and better; Mercy from Us.
So Allahسُبحانه وتعالى gave him back his family,
whether it was reviving the dead or providing him with new members of family; Allah Ho Alam(الله اعلم);
But he had equal to what he had before and even better.
So now his family was replaced.
What about his wealth?
We find that in a Hadith(حديث) narrated by Bukhari(بخاريْ);
Rasool Allah ﷺ says;
When Ayub(أيوب) was taking a shower naked;
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى sent on him grasshoppers made of gold that were falling over him.
Syedina Ayub(سيِّدنا أيوب) was gathering them and collecting them.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى told Ayub(أيوب);
Isn't it Me; Who will provide for you; So why are you gathering all of this?
He said; O Allah, this is Your mercy and I want to have more of it.
It's a miracle Allahسُبحانه وتعالى provided him with grasshoppers made of gold;
As a reward for the patience of His servant Ayub عليه السّلام.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
وَوَهَبْنَا لَهُ أَهْلَهُ وَمِثْلَهُم مَّعَهُمْ رَحْمَةً مِّنَّا
And in another Ayah(آية) Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
وَآتَيْنَاهُ أَهْلَهُ وَمِثْلَهُم مَّعَهُمْ رَحْمَةً مِّنْ عِندِنَا
رَحْمَةً مِّنْ عِندِنَا وَذِكْرَىٰ لِلْعَابِدِينَ۝
Notice this; Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
So we answered his call, we removed his distress and we restored his family to him
and the like there off along with them as a mercy from Ourselves
and a reminder for who?
وَذِكْرَىٰ لِلْعَابِدِينَ۝
The story of Ayub(أيوب); Allah is saying
that it is a reminder for Al-Aabideen(ألعابدين); the worshipers of Allah.
Notice the word Al-Aabideen(ألعابدين), when you are worshiping Allahسُبحانه وتعالى you need to have a lot of patience.
Because worshipping Allahسُبحانه وتعالى needs commitment and discipline and persistence.
This is very easy to suddenly go into an emotional outburst and pray and read Qur'an and follow the Sunnah(سنة) of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
It's very easy to do that; Sometimes we find that people crash into the religion and they start practicing;
but it's not easy to persist and continue with it.
And that is why Rasool Allah ﷺ says;
شَيَّبَتْنِي هودٌ
Hud(هود) has made my hair turn gray.
What is the Ayah(آية) in Syedina Hud(سيدنا هود) Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
فَاسْتَقِمْ كَمَا أُمِرْتَ
Stay on the straight path.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى is telling Muhammadﷺ to stick on the straight path for all of your life.
And that is Rasool Allah ﷺ is saying; It made my hair turned gray
because it is easy to worship Allahسُبحانه وتعالى for a few days and night
but to discipline yourself to do it continuously it needs patience.
To pray Witr(وتر) continuously; it need patience;
to fast; it needs patience; to pray in Jama'ah(جماعة) it needs patience;
to make Zikr(ذكر) of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى it needs patience;
that's why Allahسُبحانه وتعالى has closed the Ayah(آية) of the story of Ayub(أيوب) with this final comment,
وَذِكْرَىٰ لِلْعَابِدِينَ۝
It's a reminder for those, who are worshipping Allah.
And this is a form of Bala(بلى); This is a form of testing that Allahسُبحانه وتعالى puts on the Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء).
Rasool Allah ﷺ says;
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى tests the Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء) with the most severe tests.
And then As-Saliheen(الصالحين);
فالأمثل فالأمثل
And then the best of you.
The more strong you are and firm in your Deen(دِيْن);
the more difficult the test of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى on you; will be.
Just like in school;
The professors when they write tests, or the teachers when they write test,
they write a group of easy questions,
the average difficulty questions
and then they put a few tough questions here and there to separate between the high segment of the class.
So you have a group of questions which are easy those will be answered by the majority.
And then you have another group of questions that will be answered by a lesser group.
And that is separate between, the D and the C.
And then you have questions that will separate between the B and the C.
And then you have questions that will separate between the A and the B.
And then you have one or two questions that will separate between the A Plus and the A Minus.
So, everyone is receiving questions according to his level.
And that is to put them through this ranking;
If you made all of the questions easy, everyone will get 100% the full score and everyone will pass.
So you have to put the questions in a gradual step by step level of difficulty to separate between these students.
The same thing with the test that Allahسُبحانه وتعالى puts on us in Duniyah(دُنِيَّا).
If your Eeman(ايمان)  is weak, Allah will give you a simple exam.
If your level of Eeman(ايمان) is strong, then you would receive a more difficult exam.
And these tests that the Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء) of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى go through are more severe.
Not only, are they severe in their tests and Da'wah(دعوة), even in their illness it's more difficult.
Abdullah Ibn Masood(عبدالله ابن مسعود) was visiting Rasool Allah ﷺ his death; illness.
So Abdullah Ibn Masood(عبدالله ابن مسعود) put his hand over Rasool Allah ﷺ; temperature was so high.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
نعم إني أُوعَك كما يوعك رجلان منك
Rasool Ullah said; I go through fever that two of you would go through.
The fever on Rasool Allah ﷺ was double.
Why?
Because of the level of Rasool Allah ﷺ he had to go through more difficult tests from Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
The next story is the story of Zan-Noon(ذا النون); Sahib Al-Hoot(صاحب الحوت); Syedina Yunus عليه السّلام.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى has called him; Zan-Noon(ذا النون)
and Noon(نون) is the big fish or whale;
Sahib Al-Hoot(صاحب الحوت) is the same thing.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
وَإِنَّ يُونُسَ لَمِنَ الْمُرْسَلِينَ ۝
And verily Jonah was one of His messengers.
Syedina Yunus عليه السّلام was sent to a town in Iraq.
He made Da'wah(دعوة) to his people calling them to Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
As usual, they did not respond.
And they were harsh on him;
Syedina Yunus(سيدنا يونس) was irritated by their response and agitated.
His people provoked him because of their persistence and animosity towards the religion of Allah.
Syedina Yunus(سيدنا يونس) said;
If this is the situation with these people, they don't deserve this, I will leave and I'll go somewhere else.
I'll go and make Da'wah(دعوة) in other parts of the world, I will leave these people alone.
They don't deserve this; Look at their response.
وَذَا النُّونِ إِذ ذَّهَبَ مُغَاضِبًا
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says; And Zan-Noon(ذا النون), he left angry;
He left his people in a state of anger.
They did not respond; They don't want to listen;
I'm going to leave and go somewhere else.
So he left them, and he wants to get as far as possible; So he went in the sea.
And he took a boat to go in the sea; so it take him as far as possible from these people; who he despised.
Wind picked up, waves were getting higher and higher; It was a storm.
The people were in that boat, they decided that in order for us to survive, we have to get rid of our luggage.
They threw all of their luggage; to make the book lighter.
That wasn't enough.
So now they have to throw in; one of the passengers.
They have to throw out; one of the passengers; they have to sacrifice one of the men onboard.
So they cast lots like what we say today; throw a dice.
So they cast the lot it came on who; Yunus(يونس).
They said; No, No, No. We're not gonna get rid of Yunus(يونس); This is our Barakah(بركة); This is our blessing on the boat.
He's the best man; we have on board; We're not going to get rid of him.
Let's try again; They throw it another time.
It came on who?
Yunus(يونس);
Another time; They did it a third time; it came on Yunus(يونس).
And these people; they didn't want to get rid of Yunus(يونس).
They saw how righteous he was; They don't want to get rid of him.
Syedina Yunus(يونس) knew that this is not random.
These casting of the lots is not random;
This is by the will of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى and Allah is telling him something.
So he jumped in the sea.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى commanded one of His creation; the whale or the big fish to swallow him.
So it swallowed Syedina Yunus(سيدنا يونس).
They say; the Mufasireen(مفسرين); some of the commentators on Qur'an; they say
that Yunus(يونس) was unconscious.
And then he woke up in the stomach of Al-Hoot(ألحوت); the whale.
And he looked around him, and he thought that he is where?
In the grave.
He thought he's dead; for a while;
but that impression did not last long.
Because he started touching around him and he found out that this is not a grave, this is the stomach of a whale.
Now obviously, a stomach of a whale is not a five star hotel, it's not a comfortable place to be.
Stomach of whale is intended to do what?
To digest food.
And some of the most powerful enzymes and digesting fluids are in the stomachs of fish.
Because if you notice fish do not chew their food; they swallow it whole.
If you dissect the stomach of a fish, you would find the whole fish in there;
And they have disintegrated and melted because of the power of the enzymes; It just breaks apart the flesh.
So Syedina Yunus(سيدنا يونس), his flesh, his skin was peeling off; his flesh his skin was falling out.
The stomach did not know this is Syedina Yunus(سيدنا يونس); a Nabi(نَبِي) of Allah; it was digesting him just like any other meal.
So his skin was peeling out.
Syedina Yunus عليه السّلام in this moment of difficulty, he ran to Allahسُبحانه وتعالى; And he made Sujood(سجود)
and he told Allahسُبحانه وتعالى;
O Allah I am making Sujood(سجود) to you in a place; where no one made Sujood(سجود) to you before; in the stomach of whale.
And then he made his famous Dua(دُعَا) which was recorded in Qur'an.
He said;
فَنَادَىٰ فِي الظُّلُمَاتِ أَن لَّا إِلَٰهَ إِلَّا أَنتَ سُبْحَانَكَ
سُبْحَانَكَ إِنِّي كُنتُ مِنَ الظَّالِمِينَ۝
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
فَنَادَىٰ فِي الظُّلُمَاتِ
And he called in the darkness.
He said;
None has the right to be worshipped but You glorified and exalted be You;
Truly I have been of the wrongdoers.
An admission of guilt, and witness of the oneness of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
فَنَادَىٰ فِي الظُّلُمَاتِ
He cried in the darkness.
This was the darkness of the stomach of the whale;
In the darkness of the sea; In the darkness of the night; three darknesses.
Rasool Allah ﷺ says;
The angels see Hilkah Az-Zikr(حلقه الذكر) the meetings of remembrance of Allah; like stars,
which you see in the sky.
We use the stars to navigate;
The angels use these stars on earth to know where Allah is being remembered.
Whenever a group of Muslims come together, and we hope to be one of those.
This appears to the creation of the heavens; Like a star,
and they see it and they come to it,
so that they can witness the circles of remembering Allah and make Dua(دُعَا) for the ones; who are in it.
So we ask Allahسُبحانه وتعالى to surround us with the angels of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى
and to accept their Dua(دُعَا) and to make us of those who are forgiven.
So even though this was in the depths of the ocean;
In the middle of the stomach of the whale; in the darkness of the night;
the weak voice of Syedina Yunus(سيدنا يونس) was heard by the angels in the utmost heavens.
These angels went to Allahسُبحانه وتعالى and said; O Allah;
اليس هذا الصوت عبدك صالح فلان
Isn't this the sound of your righteous servant?
الذي ما ذال يصعد له العمل الصالح في اليل والنهار
Isn't this the sound of your righteous servant whom used to do good night and day?
يصعد له العمل الصالح
They used to say; We would see his good deeds going up in the sky in the night and in the day.
So this sound was familiar to them.
They knew who he was.
Why?
Because they would see pillars of light going up in the sky
because of his good deeds that he used to do every day and every night.
They knew; who he was; This sound was familiar to them.
They knew him;
because the good deeds are like pillars of light that traveling in the sky and reach to Allahسُبحانه وتعالى and passed by the angels.
They said; O Allah; Aren't you gonna have mercy on him?
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى said; Yes.
And then Allahسُبحانه وتعالى tells us in Qur'an, the reason why?
فَلَوْلَا أَنَّهُ كَانَ مِنَ الْمُسَبِّحِينَ ۝ لَلَبِثَ فِي بَطْنِهِ إِلَىٰ يَوْمِ يُبْعَثُونَ۝
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
If it was not for the fact that he used to remember Us before;
he would have remained in the stomach of the whale; until the day of judgment.
Because he remembered Allahسُبحانه وتعالى in moments of ease;
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى took care of him in moments of difficulty.
Rasool Allah ﷺ says;
تعرف على الله في الرخاء يعرفك في الشدة
Remember Allahسُبحانه وتعالى in moments of ease, Allah will remember you in moments of difficulty.
We need to remember Allah in our young age;
So that Allah will remember us in our old age.
Remember Allah; when you're healthy, so Allah remember you when you are ill;
Remember Allah when you have free time; So Allah will remember you, when you become busy.
Remember Allahسُبحانه وتعالى  when you are alive, so Allahسُبحانه وتعالى will remember you; when you're dead.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى took care of Syedina Yunus(سيدنا يونس) in the depths of the darkness of the sea
because of this Dua(دُعَا).
So Allahسُبحانه وتعالى freed him;
And Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
فَاستَجَبنا لَهُ وَنَجَّيناهُ مِنَ الغَمِ
So we answered his call and delivered him from the distress.
One of the companions came to Rasool Allah ﷺ and said;
Is this Dua(دُعَا) only applicable to Syedina Yunus(سيدنا يونس)?
Or would it apply to any one of us?
Meaning Can we make the use of the same Dua(دُعَا) and it will be accepted?
Rasool Allah ﷺ said; Yes; didn't you see Allahسُبحانه وتعالى said;
وَكَذَٰلِكَ نُنجِي الْمُؤْمِنِينَ۝
And thus we saved the believers.
Because Allah says; We saved Yunus(يونس) and thus we save the believers.
Therefore Rasool Allah ﷺ says;
هذا دعا الكرب
This is the Dua(دُعَا) of the distress.
If you ask Allahسُبحانه وتعالى using this Dua(دُعَا);
Allah will deliver you from your distress.
The Dua(دُعَا) again is;
لَّا إِلَٰهَ إِلَّا أَنتَ سُبْحَانَكَ إِنِّي كُنتُ مِنَ الظَّالِمِينَ۝
Yunus(يونس) was delivered out of the stomach of the whale
and he was delivered to safety on the shore.
But he did not have skin to protect him from the sunrays;
He did not have skin to protect him from wind.
So Allahسُبحانه وتعالى delivered him to the shore;
And then Allahسُبحانه وتعالى commanded a tree to go grow over Syedina Yunus(سيدنا يونس);
so that it would provide cover and shade for him and it will also provide him with food.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
وَأَنبَتْنَا عَلَيْهِ شَجَرَةً مِّن يَقْطِينٍ۝
Allah planted over him a tree of Yaqteen(يقطين).
But now Yunus(يونس) has to finish his job.
So last time, come back to his town; Go back.
So he went back to his people.
وَأَرْسَلْنَاهُ إِلَىٰ مِائَةِ أَلْفٍ أَوْ يَزِيدُونَ ۝ فَآمَنُوا فَمَتَّعْنَاهُمْ إِلَىٰ حِينٍ۝
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says; We sent him to 100,000 people or even more.
What happened?
فَآمَنُوا
They believed in him?
All of them accepted Islam.
فَمَتَّعْنَاهُمْ إِلَىٰ حِينٍ۝
So we gave them enjoyment for a while.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says that the people of Yunus(يونس) are an exception.
Because before the other nations of the Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء) were being destroyed.
But with the people of Yunus عليه السّلام; Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
فَلَوْلَا كَانَتْ قَرْيَةٌ آمَنَتْ فَنَفَعَهَا إِيمَانُهَا
إِلَّا قَوْمَ يُونُسَ لَمَّا آمَنُوا كَشَفْنَا عَنْهُمْ عَذَابَ الْخِزْيِ فِي الْحَيَاةِ الدُّنْيَا وَمَتَّعْنَاهُمْ إِلَىٰ حِينٍ۝
Was there any town that believed after seeing the punishment and its faith saved it from the punishment?
The answer is; None except the people of Yunus(يونس) when they believed;
We removed from them the torment and disgrace in their life and we gave them enjoyment in this world for a while.
It is said that when Yunus(يونس) left the punishment was hovering over them.
That's it; I mean the punishment was about to strike.
But because Yunus(يونس) left immaturely.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى held away that punishment, and then when Yunus(يونس) came, they responded,
and Allahسُبحانه وتعالى saved them from a punishment that was already hovering over their heads.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى in Surat Al-Qalam(سورة ألقلم) tells Rasool Allah ﷺ about this story.
And this was revealed in the period in Makkah.
When Rasool Allah ﷺ was receiving the same response of the people of Yunus(يونس); Rejection.
So to keep Rasool Allah ﷺ from doing the same thing that Yunus(يونس) did.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى told Muhammadﷺ about the story of Yunus(يونس)
and the first word that was used before the narration of the story is; Fasbir(فصبر).
Have Patience.
فَاصْبِرْ لِحُكْمِ رَبِّكَ وَلَا تَكُن كَصَاحِبِ الْحُوتِ إِذْ نَادَىٰ وَهُوَ مَكْظُومٌ۝
لَّوْلَا أَن تَدَارَكَهُ نِعْمَةٌ مِّن رَّبِّهِ لَنُبِذَ بِالْعَرَاءِ وَهُوَ مَذْمُومٌ۝
فَاجْتَبَاهُ رَبُّهُ فَجَعَلَهُ مِنَ الصَّالِحِينَ۝
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
So wait with patience for the decision of your Lord;
and be not like the Companion of the fish; When he cried out to us while he was in deep sorrow;
Had not the grace from his Lord reached him; He would indeed have been left in the stomach of the fish.
So he was cast off on the naked shore; while he was to be blamed;
but his Lord chose him and made him of the righteous.
So Allahسُبحانه وتعالى chose him and made him of the righteous.
صَلَّى الله عَلى سَيَّدِنَا محمد وَعَلى اَلِهِ وَ صَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ